A Finding Aid to the Martin Diamond Papers, 1928-2013, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Martin Diamond papers
1928-2013
Archives of American Art
Diamond, Martin
AAA.diammart2
Archival Resource Key
3.2 Linear feet
The papers of New York art dealer, writer and teacher Martin Diamond measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1928 to 2013. The materials involve to a limited degree Diamond's wife, Harriette Diamond, co-owner and co-operator of Martin Diamond Fine Arts, Inc. Their gallery work and relationships with artists they represented are documented by writings, subject and artist files, and photographic materials. Subject files concern American abstract art, particularly the 20th century Transcendental abstract painters, and include printed materials, correspondence and photographic materials. Artists' files include similar materials and some writings by artists. Photographic materials are of artworks and exhibition installations.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 4 series. Materials are generally arranged by record type and chronologically thereafter.
Missing Title
Series 1: Writings, 1995 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Subject Files, 1940-2008 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Artists' Files, 1928-2013 (Boxes 1-3; 2.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Photographic Materials, 1988 (Boxes 3-4; 0.4 linear feet)
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original materials requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 1993 and 2014 by Martin Diamond.
Related Materials
The Rutgers University Art Library in New Brunswick, New Jersey holds the "Martin and Harriet Diamond Vertical Files of American Art," which consists of 300 cubic feet of art exhibition catalogs dating from the late nineteenth century through the first half of the twentieth century.
Biographical / Historical
Art dealer and writer, Martin Diamond (b. 1924) owned Martin Diamond Fine Arts, Inc. with his wife, Harriette. The gallery was established in January 1976 and operated until 1986, specializing in pre-world War II American modern and Abstract Art. It then became a private gallery operating until 1996, when the couple retired. Martin Diamond was particularly interested in Transcendental Art, an area of Abstract Art focused on the artwork's spiritual qualities. His writings include Who Were They? My Personal Contact with 35 American Modernists Your Art Hisory Course Never Mentioned (1995) and his memoirs of his years as a New York City art dealer (1975-1985). Martin and Harriette Diamond presently reside in New Rochelle, New York. Artists represented by the gallery included Vaclav Vytlacil, Blanche Lazzell, and Marguerite and William Zorach.
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York art dealer, writer and teacher, Martin Diamond measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1928 to 2013. The materials involve to a limited degree Diamond's wife, Harriette Diamond, co-owner and co-operator of Martin Diamond Fine Arts, Inc. Their gallery work and relationships with artists they represented are documented by writings, subject and artist files, and photographic materials. Subject files concern American abstract art, particularly the 20th century Transcendental abstract painters, and include printed materials, correspondence and photographic materials. Artists' files include similar materials and some writings by artists. Photographic materials are of artworks and exhibition installations.
Art, Abstract; Art, Modern -- 20th century; Photographs; Art, American -- 20th century; Transcendentalism in art; Art dealers -- New York (State) -- New York; Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Gallery owners -- New York (State) -- New York; Diamond, Harriette; Martin Diamond Fine Arts (Gallery)
- Writings, 1995; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Who Were They? My Personal Contact with Thirty-Five American Modernists Your Art History Course Never Mentioned by Martin Diamond is a 61 page text, discussing how Diamond encountered many of the artists he represented and details of their lives and work.
  - Who Were They? My Personal Contact with Thirty-Five American Modernists Your Art History Course Never Mentioned, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Subject Files, 1940-2008; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  The subject files concern American abstract art and Martin Diamond's activities to educate and promote this work, particularly that of the Transcendental painters. The materials include exhibition announcements and catalogs, clippings, business records and loan agreements regarding exhibitions. There also are letters from museums relating to Diamond's participation as a lecturer in connection with exhibitions. Museums involved include the National Museum of American Art of the Smithsonian Institution, The Albuquerque Museum, the Art Gallery of Toronto, and the Boca Museum of Art in Florida as well as some New York area museums. Of particular interest is Diamond's writing explaining his relationship with Phillip Frost, who donated much of his abstract art collection to the National Museum of American Art.
  - American Abstract Art, 1952-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Abstract Art, 1991-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Abstract Art, Frost Collection, 1983-1991; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Martin Diamond Lectures, 1959-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rutgers University Library, undated; 1989-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Transcendental Painting Group, undated; 1940-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Artists' Files, 1928-2013; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 2.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Found within artists' files are photographs, transparencies and slides of artworks, exhibition announcements and catalogs, along with business and legal records of the Martin Diamond Fine Arts, Inc. There also is business correspondence with artists, museums, universities, and some greeting cards or personal letters. There is scattered biographical information about the artists as well as writings by artists, Hans Hofmann, Blanche Lazzell, Hananiah Harari and Carl Holty.
  - Theresa Bernstein, 1985-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Emil Bisttram, undated; 1971-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Harry Bowden, 1932-1989; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mary Ellen Bute, undated; 1948-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Paul Cadmus, 1987-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Arthur N. Christie, 1930-1996; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Max Arthur Cohen, 1978-1979; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Konrad Aileen Cramer, 1983-1984; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Charlotte Cushman, 1979-1989; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Stuart Davis, 1974-1976; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Eleanor De Laittre, undated; 1979-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Werner Drewes, undated; 1979-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Elsie Driggs, undated; 1934-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Jacob Epstein, undated; 1978-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ed Garman, undated; 1979-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ed Garman, 1989-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ed Garman, 1996-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dwinell Grant, undated; 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Robert Gribbroek, undated; 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - James Guy, undated; 1981-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - John Haley, 1981-1991; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hananiah Harari, 1939-2002; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lauren Harris, 1980-1987; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Marsden Hartley, 1969-2007; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Emanuel Herzl, 1933-1988; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fannie Hillsmith, 1979-1982; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hans Hofmann, 1994; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Carl Holty, 1972-2001; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Harry Holtzman, undated; 1980-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Charles Howard, undated; 1983-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Raymond Jonson, undated; 1979-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Raymond Jonson, undated; 1979-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Frederick Kahn, undated; circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Paul Kelpe, undated; 1980-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Blanche Lazzell, undated; 1938-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19-22)
  - Louis Lozowick, undated; 1973-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - William Lumpkins, undated; 1980-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - William Lumpkins, undated; 1980-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - George McNeil, undated; 1979-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - George Marinko, undated; 1983-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Agnes Pelton, 1983-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - H. Towner Pierce, 1980-2006; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Mark Rothko, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Mead Schaeffer, undated; 1942-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Morton Schaumberg, 1980-1982; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - John Sennhauser, 1978-1998; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Louis Shanker, 1981-1991; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Esphyr Slobodkina, 1980-2002; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Alfred Stieglitz, 1972-1998; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - John Von Wicht, 1966-2007; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Vaclav Vytlacil, undated; 1928-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8-12)
  - Vaclav Vytlacil Gifts, 1998-2005; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
  - Stuart Walker, 1981; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fred Whiteman, undated; 1979-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Robert Wolff, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Beatrice Wood, undated; 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Beckford Young, 1938-1983; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Janet Young, undated; 1957-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Wilfrid Zogbaum, 1977-1981; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Marguerite and William Zorach, undated; 1970-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Photographic Materials, 1988; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Photographic materials include snapshots, negatives, transparencies, and slides of representational and abstract artwork by Blanche Lazzell, many of which note titles and dates. The materials by miscellaneous artists consist of snapshots and transparencies of artworks by G.L.K. Morris, Irene Rice-Periera, Jay Van Everen, Jan Matulka, Jean Xceron, Abstract American Artists, and some unnamed works. There are slides of artworks by Emil Bisttram, Werner Drewes, John Ferren, James Guy, Carl Holty, Raymond Johnson, Blanche Lazzell, Transcendental Painting Group and Vaclav Vytlacil. The greatest numbers of slides are of works by Werner Drewes and Vaclav Vytacil, followed by works by Blanche Lazzell and James Guy.
  - Blanche Lazzell, undated; 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
  - Miscellaneous Artists, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Artwork by B-V (executed 1934-2013), undated; Archival Resource Key; Slides in 3 slide file boxes. (Box 4, Folder 1-3)